<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Sancar Adali - personal website</title>
    <link>https://adalisan.github.io/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Sancar Adali - personal website</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2016 Sancar Adali</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://adalisan.github.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>graph matching and spaces</title>
      <link>https://adalisan.github.io/post/graph-matching-and-spaces/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jul 2018 21:06:09 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://adalisan.github.io/post/graph-matching-and-spaces/</guid>
      <description>Part of my dissertation research was on the graph matching problem. For solving this problem in real settings, it is useful to think of vertices as elements of a space with the edges determining some sort of locality, (I guess this can be formalized with topology ). Then the graph/vertex matching problem becomes sort of a point cloud matching problem where you don&amp;rsquo;t know where the points are , just the neighborhood relationships between them ( several manifold learning uses these relationships to find the manifolds defined by the points ).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Migration</title>
      <link>https://adalisan.github.io/post/migrating-to-hugo/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://adalisan.github.io/post/migrating-to-hugo/</guid>
      <description>I have decided to switch to the academic theme for hugo , as it makes much more sense for a researcher. Now I just need to collect all the things I have done over the years.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing content with Markdown, LaTeX, and Shortcodes</title>
      <link>https://adalisan.github.io/post/writing-markdown-latex/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://adalisan.github.io/post/writing-markdown-latex/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Content can be written using &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/adam-p/markdown-here/wiki/Markdown-Cheatsheet&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Markdown&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/LaTeX/Mathematics&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;LaTeX math&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://gohugo.io/extras/shortcodes/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Hugo Shortcodes&lt;/a&gt;. Additionally, HTML may be used for advanced formatting. This article gives an overview of the most common formatting options.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building  R package from C codebase</title>
      <link>https://adalisan.github.io/post/building_r_package/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2014 19:55:16 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://adalisan.github.io/post/building_r_package/</guid>
      <description>I have been trying to build an R package that uses C code. I was not fast enough to get a working build for some time as it is a wrapper package around an existing C library and I wanted to submit to CRAN eventually, so I needed to get a linux and windows (32 and 64-bit) builds working correctly. Building an R package even with native R code is not easy.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>First post</title>
      <link>https://adalisan.github.io/post/2014-08-12-first-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2014 19:55:16 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://adalisan.github.io/post/2014-08-12-first-post/</guid>
      <description>I am in the process of creating my new personal website. I wanted to make it simple and based on a simple design with the option to generate pages without messing with HTML. That is why I am using Herring Cove. This may be overkill for a personal website.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>